<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preciousness of Christ to the believing-Christian Plainly and briefly set forth for the edification and consolation of believers in, and lovers of the Lord Jesus Christ. In a sermon on I Pet. 2. 7. By William Walker, B.D.</title>
            <author>Walker, William, 1623-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W432A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2119:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preciousness of Christ to the believing-Christian Plainly and briefly set forth for the edification and consolation of believers in, and lovers of the Lord Jesus Christ. In a sermon on I Pet. 2. 7. By William Walker, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Walker, William, 1623-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 82 [i.e. 32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Anne Maxwel, for Joseph Clark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  .N.T. --  Peter, 1st, II, 7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Preciouſneſs OF CHRIST To the Believing-Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Plainly and Briefly ſet forth for the Edification and Conſolation of Believers in, and Lovers of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON On 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Walker,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Anne Maxwel,</hi> for <hi>Joſeph Clark,</hi> 1667.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the deſervedly much Honoured Chriſtian Lady, the Lady</hi> Eſther Gooderick, <hi>The Vertuous and Religious Wife of the truly Noble and Chriſtian Knight, Sir</hi> Francis Gooderick, <hi>of</hi> Manby <hi>in the County of</hi> Lincoln, <hi>Chancellour of the County</hi> Palatine <hi>of</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme; <hi>and a Member of the Commons Houſe of Parliament.</hi> W. W. <hi>Wiſheth all the preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſs of Earth and Heaven, of Grace and Glory.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Ladyſhips long-continued favors to me and mine, do exact of me by way of just retribution, ſome monument of my Obligations to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip. Here therefore according to my ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities do I erect a little <hi>Pillar of Gratitude</hi> unto your name (a Name to which I am ſure Christ is precious, a Name which I aſſure my ſelf is precious unto Christ) Dedicating unto it this ſhort diſcourſe of the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> Which Monument though little, yet I hope may be lasting, becauſe that ſo long as there ſhall be believing ſouls in the world, which I perſwade my ſelf will be as long as the world ſhall last, (for all the Apostatizing of this last and worst age of the world, ſo much as it doth from the Faith of Christ) ſo long there will be ſouls in the world unto whom Christ Jeſus will
<pb facs="tcp:35829:4"/> be precious. And with thoſe to whom Christ himſelf is precious, any diſcovery, any diſcourſe of the preciouſneſs of Christ will be ſure to be in ſome esteem; and ſo this, I hope, among the rest; both becauſe the ſubject of it is ſweet, and becauſe the diſcourſe thereon is ſhort, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giving brief Hints to it, than being any full hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it. And to this paſs the world is grown, that even amongst ſome that are good, that which is good is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter liked, if there be but little of it. I ſhall not here put your Ladyſhip ſo much to the bluſh, though I ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by add a yet more lively tincture of Grace to thoſe lovely features which you have from nature, and which you keep too as you had them from nature, neither <hi>ſpotted,</hi> nor <hi>ſtained</hi> with adventitious complexion, (a rare thing in theſe Hyppocritical days of ours, when it is in the faſhion forſooth, under one hood to <hi>carry two faces,</hi> one of Gods making, and another of our own) I ſay, I ſhall not here put your Ladyſhip ſo much to the bluſh, as to lanch forth into any large diſcourſe of your many and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertues and graces; that were the way to bring Envy instead of honour upon you, and to expoſe my ſelf to be accuſed for Flattery, whilest I ſpake but the Truth. For ſo is the world now, that anothers Goodneſs is our Envy, and their Commendation for it, our Accuſation for the want of it; and what we have not of it our ſelves, must needs be flattery if aſcribed to any other: Elſe if the curious carping folks, that can eſpie a ſingle hair where it chances to lie awrie on a Ladies forehead, would look off a while. I could diſcourſe of your great Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Loyalty to your Husband; a thing which is grown to be a very conſiderable commendation now a dayes, in as much as through the like animoſity betwixt Husband and Wife, to that which was of old betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompei,</hi> whereof the one would bear no equal, and the other could brook no ſuperiour; ſome ſcarce Lords, are
<pb facs="tcp:35829:4"/> enforced to keep Houſes like Kings, that is two a piece, one for themſelves, and another for their wives. I could diſcourſe alſo of your prudent Ordering of your Family in that Christian way, that if <hi>St. Paul</hi> himſelf were on Earth, and were to write a Letter to you, as once <hi>St. John</hi> did to an Elect Lady, he would undoubtedly not let it go without a ſalutation <hi>to the Church which is in your Houſe.</hi> I could diſcourſe of your Love to the Ordinances of Christ, and of your constancy in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them, and of your Reverence and Devotion du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that attendance; which alſo is no ſmall commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in this irreligious age, wherein Gods Publike Service, anciently the Saints delight, is become the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Publick grievance; ſo that few have any affection for it, many abſent themſelves wholly from it, and of thoſe that afford their preſence at it, how many be there, of whom the Lord may justly ſay, what once of old he ſaid of the <hi>Jews, This people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me, but have removed their heart far from me,</hi> Iſa. 29. 13. Much after the rate of their carriage at a Play-houſe is the carriage of themſelves at the Houſe of God, ſave that they give not half that heed to the Preaching of the Word, which they give to the Acting of the Play. To look about them, and ſpie marvels; to ſee faſhions and studie faces, this is, (is it not) the main buſineſs that many mind whilest they are at Church, forgetting in the mean time where they are, and what they are about, and in whoſe preſence they are about it. I could diſcourſe alſo of your zeal and care to bring others to the Ordinances, as well as to come to them your ſelf. O how comely is the ſight of your Ladyſhip marching together with your Husband in the Head of your following Family to the Houſe of God! Which is ſo much the more commendable in you, in regard of the great neglect in this Point, which too many great
<pb facs="tcp:35829:5"/> ones are guilty of, who quite contrary to the temper of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> (whoſe reſolution was, that though all <hi>Iſrael</hi> beſide ſhould go away from, and forſake God, yet <hi>he and his houſe would ſerve the Lord,)</hi> are neither for ſerving the Lord themſelves, nor for having ſo much as their houſe to ſerve him; but to the great diſcountenancing of the Ministers of God, and to the great diſcouraging of Godlineſs it ſelf, <hi>the nearer</hi> they are in reſpect of dwelling to the <hi>Church, the farther</hi> in reſpect of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they <hi>are from God.</hi> I could further tell what a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious esteem you have of the Ministers of Christ, and that for <hi>their Work ſake:</hi> (Large is that ſhare of reſpect which I my ſelf have received from you, even but for my relation that I have to that work, though far ſhort from being any workman at it.) And this alſo is by much the more commendable, in regard the Atheiſme and Infidelity of this age is grown to that height, that thoſe Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Christ, and for Christ, whoſe buſineſs is the nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating of that great work of Reconciliation betwixt God and man, whom the Primitive Saints would have pluckt their eyes out for, and have given entertainment unto, even as unto Jeſus Christ, are made amongst Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, what the Apostles were amongst Jews and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, <hi>as the filth of the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things:</hi> Fellows, whom ſome account as unfit to live, as the Jews did our Saviour; to whom it would be the greatest pleaſure in the world, to have the power &amp; opportunity of ſerving thoſe ſervants of the high God, as <hi>Hanun</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> did the ſervants of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 4. or putting any other, as ill, or worſe indignity upon them. I could tell alſo of your tender Care for any poor afflicted Member of Jeſus Christ, that comes under your notice, relieving them both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually and corporally, as their wants are; which is not at any time the least commendation of a Christian Lady,
<pb facs="tcp:35829:5"/> but the greater now in regard of the deplorable neglect thereof that is generally obſervable in most places and perſons; ſo that instead of going to viſit and relieve Christ in any of his afflicted distreſſed Members, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us I fear ſhould Christ come himſelf to us in his own perſon in any afflicted condition for comfort and relief to him in his distreſſes, I ſay I fear too many of us would let him go away from us unrelieved, even as cold and comfortleſs, hungry and naked as he came. Theſe and many more things, (excellent things) I could tell of your Ladyſhip, which would be very much to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but I forbear, becauſe they would be no leſs to your envy; and leave them to God, who ſees them in ſecret, to reward them openly; only wiſhing here withall, that thoſe that do themſelves ſee the excellencies that I have mentioned in you, or by report from others ſhall hear them of you, may ſo glorifie God by a diligent imitation of them, that they may hereafter be glorified by God, in an abundant compenſation for them. And now that my Pedestal prove not too big for my Pillar, nor my Epistle too large for my little Book. I will diſmiſſe your Ladyſhip from this trouble, and leave you to the more delightful contemplation of the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him whom your ſoul loves. And as I have in my preaching commended him unto you, ſo I ſhall in my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers recommend both you, and all that is yours unto him; and rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips most devoted, as most Obliged ſervant <hi>Will. Walker.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Colſterworth,</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decmeber</hi> 1. 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35829:6"/>
            <head>The Preciouſneſs of Chriſt to the Believing-Chriſtian.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 2. 7.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you therefore which believe, he is Precious.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle having in the third verſe of this Chapter, propoſed the graciouſneſs of the Lord, (appearing in thoſe preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſweets, and rich advantages deſigned unto Believers by the Goſpel) as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to move theſe Chriſtians, to whom he writes this Epiſtle, to reject thoſe Heretical Gnoſtick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, whereby the deceivers of thoſe times went about to infuſe into the minds of men, villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, deceitfulneſs and hypocriſie, maliciouſneſs and reproachfulneſs (which he exhorts them to in the firſt verſe)—and with the ſincere and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of <hi>new-born Babes,</hi> to ſuck and drink in the pure <hi>Milk of the Word,</hi> that ſound and wholeſome Chriſtian Doctrine, which by the Orthodox Teachers of the Goſpel was afforded to them, as being the meanes whereby they ſhould grow in grace unto glory, (which he exhorts them unto in verſe the ſecond) he goeth on in verſe the fourth and fifth, to exhort them to come and conjoyn themſelves unto Chriſt, and build themſelves upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35829:7"/> him, as living ſtones, on a living foundation, and to become both a ſpiritual Houſe, and an holy Prieſt-hood, (both Temple and Prieſts) to offer up ſpiritual Sacrifices (prayers and praiſes) unto God; propoſing as an argument thereunto, the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs thereof unto God through Jeſus Chriſt; and that confirmed by a Text of Scripture, verſe the ſixth; <hi>Behold I lay in</hi> Sion <hi>a chief corner stone, elect and precious, and he that believeth on him ſhall not be conſounded.</hi> Which is, as if he had ſaid, The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is ſo ſure and ſteady, ſo choice and precious a foundation-ſtone to whatſoever is built on him, that he that buildeth on him ſhall never have cauſe to repent of, or be aſhamed of his building, as they are uſed to be, whe having built on an ill foundation, live to ſee their build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings buried in their own ruines. What is built on Chriſt will abide, what is offered unto God by him, will be accepted. Now Chriſt being this to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſoul, it rationally follows, that ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect foundation-ſtone as he is, ſhould be very high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed by it, and be very dear and precious unto it. And accordingly it follows in the words of my Text, <hi>unto you therefore which believe, he is precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words are ſet forth unto us two things.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, what Perſons they are unto whom Chriſt is precious; and they are Believers. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>unto you that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he is precious;</hi> where by the oppoſition of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>them that believe,</hi> unto <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the diſobedient</hi> in the immediate following clauſe, it is evident that by the Believers unto whom Chriſt is precious, the Apoſtle did mean obedient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſuch Believers as do obey the Goſpel of Chriſt; obey it in cordially aſſenting to the truth of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35829:7"/> things revealed in it; obey it in hopefully expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the fulfilling of the things promiſed by it; and obey it in ſincerity, performing the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in and by it. This is the firſt.</p>
            <p>The Second is, What Chriſt is unto thoſe that believe on him; and that (ſaith our Apoſtle) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> according to the Original Text; <hi>Precious,</hi> according to our Traſlation of it.</p>
            <p>This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath two ſignifications, which are Rivals in conteſt for place in this Text. Thoſe ſignifications are, <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Price.</hi> Firſt it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>Honour,</hi> as in <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 44. where our Saviour teſtifies, that a Prophet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hath no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in his own Country;</hi> ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7. where the Apoſtle appoints, that Chriſtians ſhould <hi>render to all their dues,</hi> and particularly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>honour to whom honour is due.</hi> Secondly it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Price;</hi> as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 6. where the money for which <hi>Judas</hi> ſold his Maſter is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the price of blood.</hi> So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Ye <hi>are bought with a price.</hi> Now becauſe that which gives a price, is in its degree and kind precious, therefore by an Enallage of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive for the Adjective, it may alſo ſignifie precious. To be ſure all the words in the New Teſtament, which are ſo rendered, <hi>(viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) are derived from it in this ſignification.</p>
            <p>Now according to this variety of acceptation of the word, is the Text expounded by ſeveral men after a ſeveral manner: St. <hi>Hierome, Beza</hi> and <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> take the word in the firſt ſenſe, and ſo render it, as if the Text were to be read, <hi>unto you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which believe he is an honour.</hi> And this very reading is ſo far favoured by our <hi>Church,</hi> as to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35829:8"/> admitted into the Margent of our <hi>Bibles.</hi> Again <hi>Piſcator, Tyndal,</hi> the <hi>Geneva Interpreters,</hi> and our own <hi>Bibles,</hi> both of the Old and New Tranſlation, taking the word in the latter ſenſe, render it <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious;</hi> and our late learned <hi>Paraphrast,</hi> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, the <hi>preciouſneſs,</hi> I ſuppoſe in conformity to the Context, where Chriſt is once and again, (namely in verſe the fourth and ſixth) beſide this third place, ſtyled <hi>precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to whether acceptation we take the word, the ſenſe of the Text is unqueſtionably ſound and Orthodoxal. We will therefore not reject either, but conſider and handle the Text according to both, beginning with that, which renders it <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> And the Point delivered in the Text accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Interpretation of it, is this, <hi>That Christ is an Honour unto thoſe that believe on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas thoſe feigned Deities which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Idolaters worſhip for Gods, whether they be creatures of Gods making, or of their own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, are a ſhame and a reproach to the worſhipers of them, as being but ſo many either nothings, <hi>i. e.</hi> none of the things that they are believed to be, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bſerv.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> worſhipped for, or <hi>stinking things,</hi> dunghil-gods, which it were a ſhame for any rational man to do any religious reverence, and perform any ſacred worſhip to: Yet Chriſt Jeſus, the God whom we ſerve, even that crucified Chriſt, who to the Jews is a ſtumbling block, and to the Gentiles fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is ſo far from being any reproach or ſhame, that he is an Honour and a Credit to the Believers on him, to the Worſhippers of him. Such he is as in Himſelf; Such he is in his Relations unto them; and ſuch alſo he is in that eſteem which they have of Him.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35829:8"/>
            <p> And Firſt, Jeſus Chriſt is an <hi>Honour</hi> unto them that believe on him, if conſidered as ſuch as he is in Himſelf. And what is that? Why, <hi>the only begotten Son of God,</hi> Joh. 3. 16. <hi>One</hi> with his <hi>Father,</hi> Joh. 10. 30. <hi>The Power of God, and the Wiſdome of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 24. <hi>Whom God hath exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and a Saviour,</hi> Act. 5. 31. <hi>And hath made him Lord and Christ,</hi> Act. 2. 36. <hi>The King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> Rev. 19. 16. <hi>The Judge of the World,</hi> Act. 10. 42. <hi>The Lord of glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>The mighty God,</hi> Iſa. 9. 6. <hi>The Head of all Principality and Power,</hi> Coloſ. 2. 10. <hi>Whom all things were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by and for, and by whom all things do conſist,</hi> Col. 1. 16, 17. Now Jeſus Chriſt being ſuch an one in Himſelf, what an <hi>Honour</hi> can it but be unto thoſe that believe on him, that they do believe and truſt in, worſhip and ſerve ſuch an one as he?</p>
            <p>Secondly, He is an <hi>Honour</hi> unto them that believe on him, if conſidered in his Relations unto them. What are they? We may reckon many, and all honourable. He is their <hi>Brother,</hi> Heb. 2. 1. their <hi>Husband,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 2. their <hi>Advocate,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 1. their <hi>Captain,</hi> Heb. 2. 10. their <hi>Prophet,</hi> Act. 3. 22. their <hi>Priest,</hi> Heb. 8. 1. their <hi>King,</hi> Rev. 15. 3. their <hi>Shepherd,</hi> Heb. 13. 20. their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 25. their <hi>Foundation,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 10. their <hi>Head,</hi> Eph. 5. 23. Now what an <hi>Honour</hi> is there flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from every of theſe Relations to every true Believer in Chriſt? O what an honour is it to a a believing ſoul, to have the onely begotten Son of God, the Heir of all thing, the firſt born of every creature to be its Brother? To have the Lord of life and glory to be its Huſband? To have the Son of Gods love who is in the boſome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? to be its Advocate with the Father?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35829:9"/> to have the mighty God to be the Captain of its Salvation? to have the eternal wiſdome of the Father to be its Prophet? the Holy One of God to be its Prieſt? the Head of all Principality and Power to be its King? to be a Sheep in that Flock, whereunto Chriſt is the Shepherd? to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant in that Church over which Chriſt is the Biſhop? to be a Stone in that Building, whoſe Foundation is Chriſt? to be a Member of that Body whereof Chriſt is the Head? <hi>Like the precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the head that ran down upon the beard, even</hi> Aarons <hi>beard, that went down to the Skirts of his garments;</hi> ſo the Honour of Jeſus Chriſt deſcends upon, and is derived unto evey member of his body, even the loweſt as well as the higheſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it; the meaneſt as well as the greareſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in it. <hi>Such honour have all his Saints,</hi> from the Relations which he ſtands in unto them. Such an honour he is unto them from thoſe Relations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As in Himſelf, and in his Relations unto his Saints; ſo in that eſteem which they have of him he is an Honour to them. However he be diſeſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deſpiſed and rejected of other men, <hi>(to the Jews a stumbling block, and to the Gentiles fooliſhneſs,</hi> to Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Atheiſts a ſcoffe and ſcorn) yet to the true Believers on him, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>an honour</hi> in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which they make, and in that eſteem which they have of him. Hence proceeded their name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his name upon themſelves, calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Christians;</hi> and as it were glorying in that Appellation, as did <hi>Sanctius</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> from whom no tortures could extort any other anſwer, to whatever queſtion was put to him, but this, <hi>I am a Christian.</hi> Hence their profeſſing with a kind of delight to be related as <hi>Servants</hi> unto him, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35829:9"/> intimating that relation by a frequent reſpectful calling him their <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Master. Christ Jeſus my Lord,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3. 8. Scarce would the devout Divine <hi>Mr. Harbert,</hi> even in his ordinary ſpeech, mention the bleſſed name of our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour Jeſus Christ,</hi> but he would adde unto it, <hi>My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. How ſweetly doth my Master ſound!</hi> My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter! <hi>As Ambergre eſe leaves a rich ſcent unto the Taster, ſo do theſe words a ſweet</hi> content: <hi>An Oriental fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, My Master!</hi> So he begins one of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poems, and goes on too in the ſame ſtrain. Hence again their free and bold confeſſing him, even before Kings, in times of hotteſt and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſecutions for his name; glorying in it, and counting it an honour, and an happineſs to them to ſuffer ſhame and reproach, yea torments, and death it ſelf for his Name. <hi>If ye be reproached for the name of Christ, happy are ye,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 41. who together with the reſt of the Apoſtles being beaten by the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for ſpeaking in his name, <hi>went away rejoycing that they were counted worthy;</hi> or, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, <hi>had the honour done them to ſuffer ſhame,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to be diſhonoured for his name,</hi> Act. 5. 14. In which expreſſion St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> a follower of their faith and ſufferings, doth alſo follow them; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo ſaith he of the chains, wherewith he was bound for the name and faith of Chriſt, I have been vouchſafed, counted worthy, or had the honour done me, to bear theſe bonds for the honour of God. Hence their triumphing in that great ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal both to Jews and Pagans, the only ſeeming thing of ſhame that could be objected to them, the Croſs of Chriſt. <hi>I determined not to know any</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35829:10"/> 
               <hi>thing among you ſave Jeſus Christ,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and him crucified;</hi> ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrotein his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. And in like manner to the <hi>Galatians, God forbid that I ſhould glory,</hi> ſave in the <hi>Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Christ,</hi> Gal. 6. 14. In ſo much that to confront thoſe Infidels, whether Jews or Pagans, that objected it as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto them, that they worſhipped a <hi>Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God,</hi> it was ancienty an uſe amongſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the firſt and beſt Ages of the Church (and that without incurring thereby any guilt either of Popery or Superſtition that I know of, however upon that groundleſs ſurmiſe diſliked and diſuſed by ſome of late) to apply the <hi>ſign of the Croſs,</hi> as a Badge of Honour, as well as Cognizance, to the Foreheads of Perſons baptized, <hi>in token,</hi> as our Church expounds it, <hi>that thereafter they ſhould not be aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Christ crucified; but fight manfully under his Banner against ſin, the world and the Devil, and continue his faithful Soldiers and Servants unto their lives end.</hi> And thus you ſee how, both in Himſelf, and in thoſe Relations wherein he ſtands unto Believers, and in that Eſteem which they have of him, Chriſt Jeſus is an Honour unto thoſe that do believe on him.</p>
            <p>Now this conſideration of the Honour that Chriſt is unto thoſe that believe on him, may be uſeful ſundry wayes.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, It may be a good inducement unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ingenuity to embrace, or retain the Faith of Chriſt. Chriſtianity, 'tis an honourable Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The Author of it is an <hi>Honour</hi> to thoſe that profeſs it, and that far beyond what ever the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of any Sect either amongſt Jews or Greeks was to the Sectaries of it. It may be a ſhame to the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35829:10"/> of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> to have no better than an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leptical Impoſtor to be their Leader. It may be a ſhame to Idolatrous Pagans to have the Father of lies to be the Author of their Religions. But unto the Believers in Jeſus Chriſt it cannot but be an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> that in their way they do follow him in the Truth, who is the way of Truth, to Life; yea who <hi>is the true God and eternal life,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 20.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It might be a good check to our too eager purſuit after wordly honour. Do we believe in Chriſt? 'Tis honour enough, even that for us. Chriſt is an honour to us; and what better? what greater honour can we have, or hope for, than what Chriſt is? Why do we then unwiſely neglect that which is our chiefeſt honour, and childiſhly run after gaudy baubles; needleſly proſecute inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Titles; ſuch as a man may carry on his back to Hell with him, and perhaps be helpt to be ſunk thither by? O let us content our ſelves with that honour which Chriſt is unto us, and never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our ſelves into a ſolicitous purſuit after any honour, but that which comes from God, and that which tends unto the honour of God; rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing more to have our names written in heaven, than to be aſſumed unto the higheſt honours upon earth; &amp; pleaſing our ſelves better in it to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Jeſus, than the Sons of Nobles, to be the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, than to be the Monarchs of the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It ſhould be a good Argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thoſe that believe in Chriſt, to labour to be an Honour unto Him. Do ye believe in Chriſt? Chriſt is an honour unto you, &amp; gratitude requires that you ſhould mutually be an honour unto him. They ſhould honour him, that are honoured by him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, 'tis wiſdome to be all the honour ye can unto
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35829:11"/> Chriſt. For thoſe that honour him, them will he honour, and in proportion to that honour that they are unto him; the greater that the honour is that ye are unto Chriſt, the greater ſhall that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be that ye ſhall receive from Chriſt; <hi>For he will render to every man according to his deeds,</hi> Rom. 2. 6.</p>
            <p>Perhaps ye will here ask me, how ye ſhall do to be an Honour unto Chriſt? To this I anſwer plainly and ſhortly; Lead good lives, lives made up of piety and purity, like the life of Chriſt, and ye ſhall thereby be an honour unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Our evil lives are a great diſhonour unto Chriſt. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Gub. l.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>In nobis Christus patitur opprobrium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salvian.</hi> By our means reproach falls upon Chriſt himſelf, through our evil deeds his name is blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Infidels abroad, and the Atheiſts at home. <hi>Ecce quales ſunt qui Christum colunt!</hi> See, ſay they, by way of ſcoff, what kind of perſons your Chriſtians are! 'Twere well that they would ſtop there, and that that were all. But they go on further to the diſhonour of Chriſt and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; <hi>Sancta a Christianis fierent, ſi Christus Sancta docuiſſet.</hi> Chriſtians, ſay they, would have pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed holineſs if Chriſt had taught it. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stimari de cultoribus ſuis potest ille qui colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Quomodo enim bonus Magister est, cujus tam malos videmus eſſe diſcipulos.</hi> Ye may judge of him that is worſhipped, by them that are the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of him. How can we think the Maſter good, whoſe Scholars we ſee to be ſo bad? O whoſe heart is not ready to run out at his eyes in tears of blood, to think that the evil lives of Chriſtians ſhould be ſuch a diſhonour unto Chriſt! It is too true, they are ſo, and we cannot deny it; <hi>(Pudet</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35829:11"/> 
               <hi>haec opprobria nobis &amp; dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felli)</hi> and a great ſhame it is unto us, that ſo they are, and we muſt confeſs it.</p>
            <p>On the contrary therefore, lead good lives, and ye ſhall be an honour unto Chriſt. As the goodneſs of the Scholar is the glory of the Maſter, ſo the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of a Chriſtan is the honour of Chriſt. <hi>For our light ſo to ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good works,</hi> that's the way to bring them <hi>to glorifie our Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5. 16. The <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Chriſtians unto the Goſpel of Chriſt, is matter of <hi>Glorification</hi> unto God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13. How will reaſon argue from the Life, to the Law! from the Tranſcript, to the Original! If the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtians be ſo good, how good is the Law that guides thoſe actions! If the lives of Chriſtians be ſo holy, what holineſs was there in the life of Chriſt, which is the Exampler of all that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs that is in them! When the Diſciples ſhine as ſtarrs on earth, what ſhall the glory of the Maſter be, but as that of the Sun in Heaven! That, that's the way to honour Chriſt above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods, for thoſe that honour him, to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above other men. And O, what an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement muſt this needs be unto holineſs and goodneſs, when the goodneſs of the creature ſhall be the glory of the Creator, and the holineſs of a Chriſtian the honour of Chriſt. As ever therefore ye deſire not to be a reproach and ſhame, but a reputation and honour unto Chriſt, ſo be ye holy in your lives, and godly in your converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Let every one that names the name of Christ depart from iniquity, and him that ſaith he abideth in Christ, ſo walk even as Christ himſelf walked; deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ungodlineſs and worldly lusts, and living ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35829:12"/> 
               <hi>righteouſly and godly in this preſent world;</hi> and every day more and more <hi>perfecting</hi> holineſs in the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And thus far we have diſcourſed of the Text ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that acceptation of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in it, in which it is by ſome rendred <hi>Honour.</hi> We will now, in reverence to our own Tranſlators who ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>Precious;</hi> and in reference to Authority which hath ſtamped that Tranſlation for current amongſt us; and alſo out of reſpect unto the context, wherein Chriſt is more then once termed <hi>precious;</hi> we will now (I ſay) proceed to diſcourſe of the Text according to that acceptation of the word al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And the Point delivered in the Text according to that Interpretation of it, is this, <hi>That Jeſus Christ is very precious to a true believing-Christian. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you therefore which believe</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle here) <hi>he is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even <hi>preciouſneſs</hi> in the abſtract, that is, very <hi>precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this we ſhall ſhew him to be in five reſpects. Things are precious unto men in reſpect, either firſt of their Rarity and Singularneſs; or ſecondly of their Worth and Excellencies; ot thirdly, of their Pleaſingneſs and Delightfulneſs; or fourthly, of their Uſefulneſs and Profitableneſs; or fithly, of their Needfulneſs and Neceſſarineſs. And upon all theſe conſiderations Chriſt is precious unto thoſe that believe on him.</p>
            <p>And Firſt in reſpect of <hi>Rarity and Singularneſs.</hi> Men uſe to account thoſe things precious, which are rare and ſingular; beſides which there are few, or none other of the ſame kind in being; as the <hi>Phoenix</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rare birds or beaſts, fruits or trees; &amp; upon this account is Jeſus Chriſt precious to a believing ſoul. There is no ſuch Saviour as he, no Saviour but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35829:12"/> he. <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Christ Jeſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 11. <hi>Neither is there ſalvation in any other; for there is no other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be ſaved,</hi> Act. 4. 12. Whence he is in Scripture ſtyled by way of Emphaſis, <hi>The Saviour,</hi> Joh. 4. 42. Phil. 3. 20. Now the believing ſoul being fully peſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of this, doth upon this account highly eſteem of Jeſus Chriſt; He is very dear and precious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In reſpect of <hi>Worth and Excellentneſs.</hi> Men uſe to account thoſe things precious, which are of great worth and excellency in any kind; as Gold and Pearls, and precious Stones. And upon this account is Jeſus Chriſt even <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to a believing ſoul; as being of worth above its comprehenſion, excellent beyond its imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As there is no conſiderable light in the Stars, but what is imparted unto them from the Sun; ſo there is nothing of worth or excellency in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in any part of the Creation, but what is a communicated ray of the worth and excellency that is in Chriſt, <hi>by whom all things were created and do conſist,</hi> Coloſ. 1. 16, 17. What worth, what excellency then muſt there needs be in Chriſt, from whom all worth and excellency is communicated! The particulars of his Excellencies are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the nature of them unutterable, the value of them inconceivable; they are an Ocean which knows neither bank nor bottom, every way infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and incomprehenſible. And this the Believing ſoul being fully perſwaded of, ſets a high price up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; counts him <hi>the chiefest of ten thouſand,</hi> as the Spouſe in the Canticles did her Beloved; yea <hi>worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> ſervants did their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35829:13"/> Lord. Yea were there ten thouſand times ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons of more worth and excellency than any that ever yet lived upon the face of the earth, yet in the eſteem of the Believing ſoul, they be all of no worth if compared with Chriſt, which would ſay to him in <hi>Davids</hi> words, Pſal. 73. 25. <hi>Whom bave I in heaven but thee, and there is none on earth that I deſire in compariſon of thee.</hi> In them could be but the finite worth and excellency of the Creature, in Him is the infinite worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Creator. Now betwixt finite and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite there is no proportion, and ſo there can be no compariſon. Thus precious is Chriſt Jeſus unto the Believing Chriſtian in reſpect of worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In reſpect of <hi>Pleaſingneſs</hi> and <hi>Delightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Men uſe to account thoſe things precious wherein they find much pleaſure, and take great delight; as beautiful flowers, rich perfumes, charming ayres, &amp;c. And upon this account is Chriſt Jeſus very precious to a Believing ſoul. The Spouſe in the Canticles firſt compares him to a <hi>Tree,</hi> and then expreſſeth what delight ſhe took both in his <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and in <hi>his fruit. I ſate down</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet to my tast,</hi> Cant. 3. 3. O the rare pleaſures, the raviſhing ſweets of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which true Believers have with Chriſt! Thoſe that truly believe in Chriſt are ſpiritually united unto Chriſt, and have the ſpirit of Chriſt in-dwelling in them. Now what inward joyes are, at ſome times eſpecially, communicated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſouls, what ſecreet ſweets are impreſſed upon their ſpirits by the Holy Ghoſt which dwelleth in them, cannot ſo well be told as felt. 'Tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35829:13"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as our Apoſtle tell us in the firſt chap. of this Ep. ver. 8. <hi>joy unſpeakable,</hi> ſuch as they that feel it within, yet are not able to ſpeak it out. A believing ſoul enjoying inward actual communion with Chriſt, is ſometimes as it were emparadiſed on this ſide heaven, not being with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> wrapt into the third heaven, but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Chriſt on the Mount, the third heaven brought down unto him, yea, and into him too, ſo that he hath a heaven in the very heart of him. <hi>O ſpeak it when I am gone</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>and preach it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> 
               <hi>at my Funeral: God dealeth familiarly with man, I feel his mercy, I ſee his Majesty, whether in the body or out of the body I cannot tell, God he knoweth, but I ſee things that are unutterable. I am</hi> (ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <note place="margin">Mr. Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> 
               <hi>by the wonderful mercies of Christ as full of comfort as my heart can hold, and feel nothing in my ſoul but Christ, with whom I heartily deſire to be. O</hi> (crys out a third) <hi>the joyes, the joyes, the joyes that I feel</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Kat. Brettergh.</note> 
               <hi>in my ſoul! O they be wonderful, they be wonderful, they be wonderful, &amp;c.</hi> With ſome ſuch prelibati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of bliſſe, foretaſts of happineſſe, earneſts of their promiſed inheritance, doth Chriſt ſometimes comfort the hearts, delight the ſouls, and endear to him the affections of thoſe that truly believe on him; and thence alſo he is very precious unto them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in reſpect of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs and Profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs.</hi> Men do uſually ſet a great price upon things that are greatly Uſeful and Profitable to them; as rich Land, fat Paſtures, vendible Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, helpful Engines and Inſtruments, &amp;c. And upon this account alſo is Jeſus Chriſt very precious to a believing ſoul. He is of mighty uſe, hugely advantagious to it. He is a Father to it for Care, a Brother for Love, a Head for Direction,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35829:14"/> and a Huſband for a Protection. He is the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Prophet to teach and inſtruct him; his Prieſt to ſacrifice for and bleſs him; and his King to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and reward him. Doſt thou believe in Chriſt? then let the Devil accuſe thee, Chriſt will be thy Advocate to juſtifie thee: let God be angry with thee, Chriſt will be thy Mediator to reconcile him to thee; let the Enemies of thy ſalvation oppoſe and fight againſt thee, Chriſt will be the Captain of thy ſalvation to fight for thee and defend thee. Art thou a Believer in Chriſt? then in ſickneſs Chriſt will be thy Phyſician to heal thee; in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſt will be thy Friend to comfort thee; in need Chriſt will be thy Aſſiſtant to help thee, in diſtreſs Chriſt will be thy Counſellor to adviſe thee, and in danger Chriſt will be thy Saviour to deliver thee. To the hungry, he is bread, to the thirſty, he is drink; to the naked, he is cloathing; to the deſtitute he is a covering; to the perſecuted, he is a ſanctuary; to the weak, he is ſtrength; to the blind, he is light; and unto the dead, he is life. He is wiſdom to the ignorant, righteouſneſs to the guilty, ſanctification to the polluted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to the impriſoned, ſalvation to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. In a word, to the believing ſoul Chriſt is every thing that it can want, or can deſire. And the believing ſoul being both perſwaded by <note place="margin">See <hi>S. Chryſ. Serm.</hi> 24. on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13.</note> the Goſpel, and finding by experience that he is all this unto it, upon this account alſo, as I know not how it ſhould do any other, holds him excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dear and precious to it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, in reſpect of <hi>Neceſſaries</hi> in order to the Believers happineſs. Men do uſually make great account of, and eſteem very precious ſuch things as they muſt needs have, and can no wayes be, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35829:14"/> be well without; as meat in hunger, clothes in cold, Phyſick in ſickneſs, &amp;c. And even upon this account is Chriſt Jeſus exceeding precious unto thoſe that believe on him. They know that there is no ſalvation to be had without him; that there is no other Saviour beſides him, there is no other name under heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved, but his only. They know that without him there would be none to give them any inſtruction, or to make for them any ſatisfaction, or to afford them any protection; that without him they could neither be juſtified from guilt, nor ſanctified from corruption, nor redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from damnation; that without him they could neither do any thing but ſin, nor expect any thing but puniſhment, nor be any thing but the miſerable objects of Gods wrath, and the Devils malice, the power of Death, and the plagues of Hell; and therefore upon this abſolute neceſſity that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend themſelves to have of him, he is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly dear and precious unto them.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewn you, both that Chriſt is very precious unto them that believe on him, and alſo upon what account it is, that he is ſo precious to them. The point will be uſeful two wayes; firſt by way of Examination, and then by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; unto both which I now proceed.</p>
            <p>And Firſt for <hi>Examination.</hi> You ſee Brethren that Chriſt is precious unto them that do truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him; examine your ſelves a while now, whether he be ſo to you, or no. By ſuch exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation you may come to underſtand ſomething of your own condition, and diſcern whether you be in the faith or no; whether you believe, or do not believe in Chriſt; or at leaſtwiſe what kind of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35829:15"/> in Chriſt you are: Well then the queſtion is, Is Chriſt Jeſus precious to you? That which is precious to a man, Firſt he will have his mind much and often upon; Secondly, he will highly prize it; Thirdly, he will greatly deſire it; Fourthly, he will diligently ſeek it; Fifthly, he will dearly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it; Sixthly he will carefully keep it. And ſo it is with thoſe to whom Chriſt Jeſus is precious. By theſe notes Believers do uſe to evidence the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of Chriſt to them; by theſe notes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do you examine your ſelves about Chriſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe unto you, &amp; by that examination try the truth, and ſee the ſlrength of your faith in Chriſt. And firſt, they to whom Chriſt is precious, will have their hearts and minds much and oft upon him. A mans heart will be much upon his treaſure, and ſo will the Believers heart be much upon Chriſt; he thinks he can never have his fill of thinking of him; and wiſhes to ſpend eternity in that communion with him. But becauſe the Bow cannot always be at full bent, and the affairs of this temporal life do neceſſitate frequent interruptions of that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual commerce, therefore he is forced to give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to other cogitations; but yet as if they were but only occaſional diverſions, and not the buſineſs of his life, he returns eftſoons after every interruption to his main concerning meditation. An evidence whereof we may have in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, who did ſeperate not only a week of extraordinary days in every year, but one Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary day in evry week, ye and I had almoſt ſaid a week of hours in every day to acts and exerciſes of holy communion with him, praiſing him with <hi>David ſeven times a day,</hi> and <hi>riſing with him at Midnight</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to praiſe him; and all this, beſides what came in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35829:15"/> by the by, in occaſional ejaculations and devotions, in reſpect of which they might beſaid to <hi>pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> and even <hi>without ceaſing.</hi> Now Chriſtians, examine your hearts; how ſtand they towards Chriſt? is their inclination, like that of the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle towards the pole, continually moving towards him? Do your <hi>ſouls</hi> like <hi>Davids,</hi> (Pſal. 63. 8.) <hi>hang upon him,</hi> and <hi>follow hard after him?</hi> Upon every interruption do your <hi>ſouls,</hi> like the Spouſes ſoul in the <hi>Canticles, c.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>make you like the Charrets of Aminadib,</hi> hot and ſwift in the retirement of him? Plainly and ſhortly, Is it a ſweet thing to you to meditate upon him? And do you exerciſe your ſelves much in that converſe with him? Are you often thinking of him? And do you delight in ſuch thinking? Then 'tis a ſign you have ſome value for him, that he is precious unto you. But if the world, or any thing in it, take up the whole, or the remain of your hearts, ſo that your minds are little or nothing upon Chriſt, and you are ſeldome or never thinking of him, it is a ſign Chriſt is not very precious to you. Small is the value we have for that, which we are ſeldome or never thinking of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they to whom Chriſt is precious, as they will be much and often thinking of him, ſo they will ſet a high price and value upon him, they will very highly prize him. His <hi>worth</hi> with them <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Rubies, and all the things that may be deſired are not to be compared to him,</hi> Prov. 8. 11. Like St. <hi>Paul, they will count all things but loſs and dung in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with him,</hi> Phil. 3. 8. Now Brethren, is it ſo with you? Have you ſuch high thoughts of Chriſt? Do you ſet ſo great a price upon him? Do you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a Divine nature and excellency, an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35829:16"/> worth and value in him? Is there nothing that your heart can prefer before him? It is then a ſign he is precious to you. But if your thoughts touching his nature and excellency be mean and low, ſo that like the <hi>Arian Hereticks</hi> of old, and the <hi>Socinian Hereticks</hi> of late, you eſteem him but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a meer man; if his worth and value in your apprehenſion be ſcanty and little, ſuch as it was in his, who ſold him for thirty pence; (and it is ſad to think how many there be at this day that matter not the ſelling of him at a much lower rate;) if there be any thing that you prize above him, or prefer before him, then it is a ſign that in your eyes he is <hi>deſpiſed, and you esteem him not,</hi> that you make no great account of him, that he is not precious to you. Thoſe things are not precious to us, which we have but little value for.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They to whom Chriſt is precious, have a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ignat. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi>
               </note> very great deſire after him. They hunger after him, they <hi>pant and breath after him, even as the Hart pants and brays after the Water-brooks;</hi> their <hi>Souls,</hi> like <hi>Davids,</hi> are <hi>athirst for God,</hi> (Pſal. 42. 1, 2.) <hi>for the living God; they count all things,</hi> like St. Paul, <hi>but loſs and dung, that they may win Christ.</hi> Phil. 3. 8. <hi>O my Dove, that art in the clefts of the Rocks, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places of the stairs, let me ſee thy Countenance, let me hear thy Voice, for ſweet is thy Voice, and thy Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is comely:</hi> So breaths the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> after Chriſt her beloved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 14. Chriſt is the deſire of the ſouls of them that truly believe in him, and their hearts do even run after him with the ſwifteſt feet of the ſtrongeſt affections. Is it ſo with you Brethren? Examine your hearts upon this Point. Have you ſo fervent a love for your Lord? Have you ſo paſſionate affections for Jeſus? Have you ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35829:16"/> ſtrong deſires after Chriſt? Is the deſire of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the delight of your ſouls? Anſwerable unto his preciouſneſſe to you will be your affections for, your love to, your deſires after him. But if your affection for him be ſmall, your love cold, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire weak, it is a ſign he is not precious to you. That is not very precious to a man, which he hath no great love for, nor mind to, nor deſire after.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they to whom Chriſt is precious, will be very induſtrious in their Inqueſt after him; they will <hi>ſeek him diligetly even as ſilver, and ſearch for him as for hidden treaſures,</hi> Prov. 2. 4. <hi>or as a Merchant ſeeks for goodly Pearls,</hi> Mat. 13. 45. they will <hi>ſeek him,</hi> like the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> by <hi>night, upon their beds,</hi> and <hi>by day in the streets,</hi> and <hi>in the broad wayes,</hi> Cant. 3. 1, 2. in private duties, in publick Ordinances, any where, every where, wherever they may hope to find him, neglecting no means, refuſing no pains, miſſing no opportunities of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him. Is it ſo with you Brethren? Are you diligent in your ſearch after Chriſt? Can you find in your hearts to be at paines to ſind him? Do you think no labours, no watchings, no faſtings, no prayers, no teares, no attendance in duties, and on Ordinances too great ſo you may win Chriſt? It is then a ſign Chriſt is precious to you. But if you make little or no inquiring after him, if you be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and lazie in the ſeeking of him; if you think much and grudge to be at paines to find him, it is a ſign you ſet ſmall value upon him, that you have no precious eſteem for him. It is not precious to a man that is not worth his ſeeking after.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they to whom Chriſt is precious, will be willing to purchaſe him at any rate, though never ſo dear, ſo they may but have him. They will part
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35829:17"/> even with all for him. Like the Merchant in the Goſpel that ſought for goodly pearls, when they have found <hi>this one Pearl of great price,</hi> they will ſell all they have, that they may buy him. They will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe their Liberties for Chriſt; they will forgoe their eſtates for Chriſt; they will forgoe their Honours for Chriſt; they will forgoe their Friends for Chriſt; they will forgoe their ſins for Chriſt; they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe their righteouſneſſe for Chriſt, and they will forgoe even their lives for Chriſt <hi>I have goods, a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Copin.</note> 
               <hi>Wife and Children,</hi> (ſaid a French-Confeſſor once) <hi>and yet I have lost thoſe affections which I formerly bore to them, neither are they dear to me, ſo I may gain Christ. I love my wife and children in the Lord,</hi> ſaid an Engliſh <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oodman.</note> Martyr, <hi>and if I had ten thouſand pound in gold, I had rather forgoe it all, than them: but I have them as if I had them not, and I will not for their ſakes forſake Christ. What things were gain to me,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>thoſe I counted loſs for Christ. Yea doubtleſs, and I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all tbings, and do count them but dung that I may winne Christ.</hi> Phil. 3. 7, 8. It were eaſie to be very large, even ſo as to tire you with ſuch like inſtances as theſe, of Perſons who have been willing at any rate to purchaſe Chriſt, <hi>weighing neither things viſible nor things inviſiblr,</hi> as St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaid by himſelf, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for the gaining of Christ.</hi> But how is it now with you Brethren? Are you ſo fond of this great purchaſe? Are you willing to part with any thing, yea even with all thing for Chriſt? Have you nothing but what you can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily forgoe for him, however otherwiſe dear and delightful it be to you? Then it is a ſign that in your eſteem of him Chriſt is precious. But if there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35829:17"/> be any enjoyment, whether of Liberty or Eſtate, Honour or Friend, Sin or Duty, yea if it be even Life it ſelf, which you are not contented to part withall for Chriſt, I ſhall leave it unto your ſelves to conſider whether Chriſt be precious unto you or no. It is not precious which one would not part with a Vanity for; And what is the beſt of earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and enjoyments more! <hi>Vanity of vanities,</hi> ſaith the Preacher, <hi>Vanity of vanities, all is vanity,</hi> Eccl. 1. 2</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They to whom Chriſt is precious, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got him, are careful to keep him. When the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> had found him whom her ſoul loved, O how careful was ſhe to keep him! <hi>I held him,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>and would not let him go, until I had brought him into my Mothers houſe, and into the Chambers of her that conceived me,</hi> Cant. 3. 4. Chriſt when once gained, is too precious, the believing-ſoul thinks, for her to be ever willing to part with again; and therefore ſhe uſeth no leſs care to keep him, than ſhe took pains to get him. O how ſhe clings to him, and claſps about him with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfulleſt arms of pureſt Love! No man is more careful to preſerve a Jewel, than a believing-ſoul is to keep its Jeſus. She Cabinets up this Pearl of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable price, in the innermoſt Cloſet of her heart. And as if ſhe could never think him ſafe enough, ſhe is continually viſiting of him there. Like the man in the Comedy, that had found and hid a pot of Gold, her eye or mind is ſeldom off <note place="margin">Plaut. Aulut.</note> from him. Nor will ſhe upon any terms do any thing that may vex him thence; as well knowing, that if once upon any unworthy uſage he withdraw himſelf, it is no eaſie matter to recover him again. Here therefore ſhe beſtoweth all her care<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> exerciſeth all her skill how ſhe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35829:18"/> her Beloved, how ſhe may everlaſtingly enjoy her Deareſt one. And how is it now with you Brethren? are you ſo careful to keep your Chriſt? are you ſo fearful to loſe your Jeſus? are you ſo cautious not to do any thing whereby he may be provoked to withdraw himſelf from you? If ſo, then it is a ſign he is precious to you. But if you have ſmall or no regard to the holding of ſo precious a poſſeſſion as Chriſt is; if you ſlight ſuch a Friend when he is come to you; if you abuſe him, or by any unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy carriage towards him, do provoke him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from you, then it is a ſign you do not much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him, that you ſet no very great value upon him. Not very precious are thoſe things to us, which when we have them, we care not whether we loſe or keep them.</p>
            <p>I may yet over and above all theſe Notes, add in the ſeventh place, That they to whom Chriſt is precious, do preciouſly eſteem of any thing that is Chriſts; any thing that bears upon it the ſtamp and ſignature of Chriſt; any thing that hath rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Chriſt, as the Members of Chriſt, the Miniſters of Chriſt, the Word of Chriſt, the Name of Chriſt, the Day of Chriſt, and the Houſe of Chriſt. They to whom Chriſt is precious, will have a precious eſteem for all theſe. His Members they refreſh as his own bowels; his Miniſters they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as his own ſelf; his Word they hear as his own voice; his <hi>Name</hi> (that Name which is above every Name, his Name Jeſus) they do account with St. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> to contain <hi>a thouſand treaſures of good</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4. <hi>in</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>things;</hi> and will not hear it named, eſpecially in Divine Service, without ſome token of an eſpecial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. His <hi>Day</hi> with St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they account <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35829:18"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Queen and higheſt of all Dayes, and call his Sabbath a delight. And for his <hi>Houſe,</hi> with the Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> they account it no other but <hi>the Houſe of God, and the Gate of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Now Brethren, how is it with you as to theſe things? Have you ſuch dear affections for any thing that is Chriſts? Have you ſo precious an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for any of the Relatives of Chriſt? If ſo, 'tis well; it is a ſign of a good eſteem that you have of Chriſt himſelf, and that he is precious unto you. But if not (and there be too many that with their mouths do ſhew much love to Chriſt, who in their hearts have love little enough for the <hi>Members</hi> of Chriſt, leſſe for the <hi>Word</hi> of Chriſt, and leaſt of all for the <hi>Ministers</hi> of Chriſt; too many there be that pretend to be great honourers of Chriſt, that ſhew no more reſpect to the Name of Chriſt, than to any other Name; not much more reſpect to the <hi>Day</hi> of Chriſt, than to any other day; and as little (if not leſs) reſpect to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of Chriſt, as to any other houſe) I ſay, if that be not precious to you, which is Chriſts, it is to be feared, that you do but pretend, all the while that you ſay, That Chriſt is precious unto you.</p>
            <p>And now Brethren, if upon examination of your ſelves by theſe Notes, you find that Chriſt is precious unto you, ye may comfort your ſelves with a confidence of your being in the Faith of Chriſt. <hi>For unto thoſe that believe in him, he is precious.</hi> But on the other ſide, if upon this examination you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find Chriſt precious to you, ye may do well to conſider whether ye be in the faith or no. If he be precious unto thoſe that believe on him, then how can thoſe be thought to believe on him, to whom he is not precious?</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35829:19"/>
            <p> And therefore (to proceed in the ſecond place, from <hi>Examination</hi> unto <hi>Exhortation)</hi> to the end you may be able to aſſure your hearts of the truth of your faith, that ye do in truth believe in Jeſus, labour, O labour that Chriſt may be precious unto you. He is infinitely precious in himſelf; O never leave till he be anſwerably precious unto you. Theſe two are very diſtant things, for Chriſt to be preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in himſelf, and to be precious unto us. VVe cannot make him more precious then he already is in himſelf. To that which is infinite can nothing be added to make it more infinite; and 'tis infinite the preciouſneſſe that is in Chriſt. But we may make him much more precious unto our ſelves, then as yet he hath been to us. The Jewel in the Table was perfectly poſſeſſed of all its genuine native worth, at the ſame time when the dunghil-Cock preferr'd a barlie-corn before it. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt was the <hi>brightneſs of his Fathers glory, and the expreſs image</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of his perſon,</hi> (Heb. 1. 3.) even then when in the ſight of men <hi>he had no form, nor comlineſs, nor beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that they ſhould deſire him.</hi> He was <hi>choſen of God and precious,</hi> even then when <hi>he was deſpiſed and rejected of men.</hi> He was <hi>the Lord of glory,</hi> even then when the Jews his own people <hi>denyed and crucified him.</hi> That therefore being precious in himſelf, he may be precious unto you; That's the thing I exhort you to labour for. O labour to endear Chriſt to your ſouls.</p>
            <p>Now if any would know how to do this, Two Directions I ſhall give him in this caſe. Firſt let him ſtudy the <hi>worth</hi> that there is in Chriſt; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly let him conſider the <hi>need</hi> that he hath of Chriſt. If there be any man to whom Chriſt is not precious, ſurely it is upon one, or both of theſe points: either firſt becauſe he is not ſufficiently informed of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35829:19"/> the due worth of Chriſt, or elſe ſecondly, becauſe he is not truly ſenſible of the great need that he hath of Chriſt. That therefore he may be precious unto you, be much and oft upon theſe Meditations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Study the worth of Christ;</hi> conſider the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous excellencies, that with moſt illuſtrious beams do ſhine forth in him, and that whether you look upon him <hi>as God,</hi> or <hi>as Man,</hi> or <hi>as Meditator</hi> betwixt God and Man.</p>
            <p>Look upon him, Firſt <hi>as man,</hi> and how can ye but admire the exemplary holineſſe of his life! <hi>He knew no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth.</hi> How can ye but admire the inſuperable patience of his Death! <hi>He was led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, and as a lamb is dumb before the ſhearer, ſo opened he not his mouth.</hi> Laſtly, how can ye but admire the incomparable charity which he ſhewed both in his life and death! In his life <hi>he went about doing good, and healing all manner of diſeaſes and ſickneſs of the people.</hi> In his death he prayed to his Father for pardon for his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Crucifiers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Look upon him as <hi>Mediator,</hi> and acting in all his ſeveral offices. And how can ye but admire the excellencies of his Teachings as a <hi>Prophet! Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious words proceeded out of his mouth. Never man ſpake as he ſpake.</hi> How can ye but admire the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of his Sacrifice and Interceſſion as a Prieſt! Thereby he made ſatisfaction unto God for our ſins; and makes our Perſons acceptable unto God. And how can ye but admire the magnificency of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Regal Government as a King! Thereby he reſcues us from the power, malice, and injuries of all our enemies, whether they be Sin or Satan, Death or Grave, World or Hell; and both at preſent tranſlates us into a Kingdom of Grace, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35829:20"/> will hereafter eſtate us in a Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If you are able, look upon him <hi>as God.</hi> And how can ye but admire the incomparable greatneſs of his Power! He is Omnipotent; <hi>nothing too hard for him, he can do all things.</hi> How can ye but admire the incomprehenſible deepneſſe of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom! He is Omniſcient, <hi>his understanding it is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; he knows all things.</hi> And how can ye but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the unmeaſurable largeneſs of his goodneſs! He is <hi>Omnibenificent,</hi> good to all, <hi>and his mercy is over all his works.</hi> Yea not an Attribute of his, but may be a Subject for Angels to contemplate upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and even they too will come ſhort of comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the full of it, and loſe themſelves at la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into high admirings and holy adorings of him for it.</p>
            <p>O meditate my Brethren, much and oft upon theſe things. And when you find that the Lord whom you ſerve, the Jeſus whom you believe in, the Chriſt in whom ye put your truſt, is ſo glorious a God, ſo gracious a Man, ſo efficacious a Mediatour betwixt God and Man, you will find your hearts carried ſtrongly forth in high and lofty affections toward him, ſo that his perſon will be dear, his name ſweet, and the very thought of him precious to your ſouls.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the <hi>Need</hi> you have of Chriſt; which will appear by conſidering the utter undon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your condition without Chriſt. The want of this conſideration is one cauſe why it is that to many men Chriſt is no more precious than he is. They ſet no price upon him, becauſe they diſcern not their need of him. O call yourſelves to a ſtrict account, and commune with your own hearts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently about this; even what need you have of Chriſt. And that as we noted, you will quickly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35829:20"/> when once ye come to underſtand the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſs of your eſtate without Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And alas! What is man without Chriſt? An ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to God, a ſervant to ſin, a ſlave to Satan, a Child of wrath, a Captive to Death, a brand of hell. Now ſurely to be in this eſtate is a fearful thing. And to him that rightly underſtands the fearfulneſs of this eſtate, nothing can be imagined more needful, than that by which he may be delivered out of, and freed from this eſtate. Why, there is no deliverer of any from this eſtate but Chrlſt; there is no deliverance for any from it, but by Chriſt. O how precious then muſt Chriſt needs be to a poor creature that is terrified with the fearful apprehenſions of his being in ſo woful a condition. Never was ſight more welcome to man that was blind, never feet more acceptable to him that was lame, never health more desirable by him that was ſick, never liberty more dear to him that was impriſoned, never pardon more precious to him that was condemned, than Chriſt would be to ſuch a ſoul.</p>
            <p>Let me put a few Queries into your mouths to ask your ſelves about this buſineſſe, when you are at your beſt leiſures. Have you given a perfect unſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Obedience to the whole Law of God in every point of it? If ſo, then you may challenge life from God as due debt, upon the ſcore of his promiſe, <hi>This do and live.</hi> But if not (as ſure you have not, <hi>for there is none that liveth, and ſinneth not)</hi> then, are you able to bear that curſe of the Law which is due to him <hi>that continueth not in every thing that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of the Law to do it?</hi> Are you able to dwell to all eternity with devouring fire? If not that (for who is able to dwell with everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?) then are you able to free your ſelves from it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35829:21"/> either firſt by powerful <hi>reſistance,</hi> not ſuffering the ſentence to be put in execution? or ſecondly by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive <hi>eloquence,</hi> ſoftning the Judge to a revoking of the ſentence of your condemnation? Or thirdly, by prevalent <hi>interceſſion</hi> of interpoſing friends, men or Angels, extorting from him a pardon for your tranſgreſſion? Or fourthly, by <hi>giving</hi> unto Juſtice in ſome way of Commutation a full and valuable <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction?</hi> If your deliverance from eternal dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be neither to be wrought any one of theſe wayes, nor be obtained any other way beſide theſe, but only through the <hi>Redemption that is in Jeſus Christ,</hi> and that invaluable merit of his moſt precious blood, there needs no more, ſure, to tell you what need ye have of Chriſt. How can a ſoul fully convinced of this, but cry out for Chriſt, as <hi>Rachel</hi> did for Children, <hi>Give me Christ, O give me Christ or elſe I die.</hi> If ever there were any of you brought into that condition, experimentally to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the miſerableneſs of the caſe of a man without Chriſt, that is of a ſinner without a Saviour, I know your experience will confirm my ſayings.</p>
            <p>Let me yet add, Which of you is able to overcome a temptation without ſtrength from Chriſt? Which of you ſufficient himſelf to perform a good action (yea even think a good thought) without grace from Chriſt? O what is the beſt of us but a with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red branch if ſeparate from communion with Chriſt? The all that we can do without him, is juſt nothing at all. In a word, if all the hope of your accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with God, of your Reſurrection unto life, and of your Reception into Glory be founded upon Chriſt, and Chriſt alone, then underſtand your need of Chriſt; and accordingly as you need him, ſo eſteem of him. If ſuch extream <hi>need</hi> of Chriſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35829:21"/> as in you, added unto ſuch exceeding <hi>Worth</hi> as in Chriſt, be not enough to render him precious to you, who is able to imagine what ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? The Lord help you to ſuch a frame of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as that Chriſt Jeſus may be precious to you.</p>
            <p>And yet I might further add, Firſt, That to have a precious eſteem of Chriſt, is the way to be preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed of by Chriſt. If Chriſt be in your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem a pearl of great price, you ſhall be in Chriſts eſteem jewels of no little price. Not the leaſt drop of reſpect you ſhed on him, but ſhall be ſhowred back manifold upon your ſelves. And this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. There's a ſweet bleſſing pronounced on all thoſe that are ſincere lovers of Chriſt, by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the cloſe of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> c. 6. v. 24. <hi>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus Christ in ſincerity, Amen.</hi> Grace, what's that here? Why, the love, the favour, the mercy, the kindneſs of God, expreſſing it ſelf in bleſſings from God. This grace the Apoſtle prays that it may, and according to his prayer, moſt aſſuredly it will be with the ſincere lovers of Jeſus Chriſt, unto whom he is precious.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I might add, That not to have Chriſt precious unto you, is the next to your making light of Chriſt, If he that is not a lover of his brother be in Gods account a murderer of his brother, O take heed that your not having a high eſteem of the Son of God, be not in the account of God <hi>a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Son under foot.</hi> And as the other was comfortable, ſo this is terrible. There is a bitter curſe denounced againſt all thoſe that are not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Chriſt by St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo in the cloſe of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> c. 6. v. 23. <hi>If any</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35829:22"/> 
               <hi>man love not the Lord Jeſus Christ, let him be</hi> Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Maranatha. Let him be <hi>Anathema, Maranatha;</hi> what's that? Why let him fall under the heavie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cenſures of the Church, be excommunicated to the ſevereſt degree of excommunication; cut off from all communion with the Church of Chriſt, and conſequently from all union and communion with Chriſt himſelf (as he deſerves to be that makes light of Chriſt.) And what more ſad c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tion than this can a man be in on this ſide hell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>But I am loth to draw away your minds too far from the two former conſiderations, namely that of the <hi>worth</hi> of Chriſt, and that of your <hi>want</hi> of Chriſt, which alone are ſufficient to endear him very much unto you and therefore to give you room for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eon, I ſhall here break off, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ourſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35829:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
